HECTOR JAVIER HERRERA ESPINOLA

Data Scientist | Data Analyst | Data Engineer

	herrerae.hj@icloud.com
	herrerae.hj@icloud.com

+353 871864406 Cork, Ireland in LinkedIn Portfolio Site

I am a highly qualified professional with a Degree in Industrial Engineering, a certification as a Data Scientist and over 12 years of experience in areas of procurement, engineering, management, and data science within different industries. I have developed my excellent communication and negotiation skills, teamwork, people management and problem-solving skills. I have experience with data analysis using programming languages such as Python and SQL, performing ETL processes and, data visualization using Power BI and Tableau.

CORE SKILLS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- ✓ Project management: Source resources for projects, ensuring software, hardware, and appropriate staff are available to enable project completion with experience in agile methodologies.
- ✓ Excellent negotiation: Outstanding communicator with a proven track record of negotiation and strategic advancement to maximise quality and reduce costs, have procured and managed contracts obtaining unprecedentedly beneficial terms for Fortune-500 companies such as Petronas and IBM. Was officially recognised as "Best IBMer of the Quarter" in this regard.
- ✓ Highly analytical and data-driven: Experienced in ETL, database management, and data visualization.
- ✓ Result-oriented: Dedicated to achieving and surpassing targets, such as generating an 8% revenue increase as a Data Analyst, and 7-figure annual savings as a Sr. Buyer with Mercado Libre, among others.
- ✓ Languages: Spanish (Native), English (C1), Portuguese (B2), Japanese (A2).

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, SQL and Visual Basic
- Data Visualization Tools: Power BI (DAX, power queries), Tableau (VizQL), MS Excel (Pivot Tables, Macros)
- Data Analysis Tools / Libraries: Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit learn, Spicy.
- Big Data: Mongo DB, Spark, Hadoop
- Machine Learning: Supervised and Unsupervised Learning, Keras & TensorFlow
- APIs: Flask, FastAPI
- Cloud: AWS (S3, RDS, EC2)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Outer Rim | Data Analyst

Ireland | Oct 22- At present time

- Collaborated with the business intelligence team to analyse the information providing by customers and supporting on the creation of pipelines from the process of Extract, Transform and Load to connect it in a data base.
- Utilized python to ETL process to transform data and assist in the development and maintenance of data quality
- Provide robust, reliable business reporting and analysis in a user-friendly format using mostly Power BI.

Mercado Libre | Sr. Procurement Data Analyst

Argentina | Dec 2019 to Dec 2021

- Provided analytical and project management support for the LatAm region.
- Responsible for maintaining and improving the quality of data used for spending analysis and reporting for the organization.
- Ensures quality of data by interpreting patterns and trends using advanced digital tools and methods including data modelling and data mining using python, excel and SQL.
- Create dashboards to share the findings with the procurement team and other areas.
- Spearheaded the implementation of SAP Ariba Catalog across the region, streamlining the purchasing process and enhancing procurement compliance, which represented a paradigm shift within the company.
- Generated 7-figure savings annually by securing a service contract with a Human Resources company across various countries in the LatAm region.

- •Led IT Purchasing Department comprised of 4 procurement professionals.
- •Spearheaded the unification of all purchasing departments in the region into one department based in Argentina,
- •transitioning all purchase contracts to the new department within one year, generating major savings.
- •Enhanced the purchase process of laptops for the region, standardising the acquisition of a specific brand and model to be used across all countries in the region.
- •Spend analysis for the region to reach the goals and targets of the company, using advance excel skills.

Petronas| Procurement ExecutiveArgentina | Apr 2016 to July 2018| Sr. Procurement AnalystArgentina | Dec 2015 to Mar 2016

- •Managed purchases for a construction project to facilitate the launch of an energy plant, sourcing and procuring purchase contracts for electric and steam generators, as well as hiring piping and engineering contractors, among others, while delivering on quality, price, process, and efficiency.
- •Set up the Procurement department from scratch, creating enhanced and unified purchase protocols that replaced segmented purchase processes by different departments within the company, such as Finance and Operations, among others.
- •Improved customer relationships and service as a direct result of the above-mentioned Procurement department, made up of 3 dedicated procurement professionals, contributing to a strategic vision for purchasing and contracting goods and services.
- Leveraged renegotiated payment terms of various contracts, increasing average payment time frame with our 10 main providers from 15-30 days to 60-150 days, which had a direct and positive impact on cash flow.
- •Promoted to Procurement Executive due to my unaverred commitment to excellence, and my outstanding organisational skills.

IBM | Regional Sourcing Buyer

Argentina | Jan 2012 to Dec 2015

- Developed and implemented strategic sourcing plans for various software-related categories across the region.
- Procurement data analysis for all the region to measure the department's goals.
- •Officially recognised as "Best IBMer of the Quarter" in the last quarter of 2013 for my outstanding professionalism, commitment to quality, and my contributions as a contract negotiator.

EDUCATION

Soy Henry Bootcamp | Data Scientist

Remote | Sep 2022 to Jan 2023

Full time data science bootcamp. Five months of duration and more than 700 hours of training

National Technological University | Industrial Engineering

Argentina | Jan 2008 to Dec 2021

Orientation in Management and Planning

CERTIFICATIONS

University of Michigan (Coursera) | Python for Everybody Specialization Remote | July 2022

In-Company Training with IBM | Negotiation skills

Argentina | October 2014